<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Entire vindication of Dr. Sherlock against his numerous and uncharitable adversaries to his late book called The case of allegiance &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69974</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3138</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09546759</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09546759</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43577</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69974)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43577)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1008:1 or 1330:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Entire vindication of Dr. Sherlock against his numerous and uncharitable adversaries to his late book called The case of allegiance &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. 31.</note>
                  <note>Duplicate copies appear on reels 1008 and 1330.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. --  Case of the allegiance due to soveraign powers.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43577:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43577:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An ENTIRE VINDICATION OF Dr. Sherlock, AGAINST HIS Numerous and Uncharitable ADVERSARIES, To his Late Book, called, <hi>The CASE of Allegiance,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Licens'd,</hi> Decemb. 30. 1690.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers-Hall.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43577:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43577:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>'TIS a tickliſh Task I have undertaken, to write to juſtifie the Man, and yet not entirely to eſpouſe his Cauſe, to vindicate the oppreſs'd, and yet at the ſame time not to maintain all his Proceedings; I ſay, this may look ſeemingly a Contradiction to ſome Men, that carry not a due Charity in their Cenſures; but to him that follows the pure and ideal Feature of Vertue, it will look as rational and accountable, as the compleateſt Vindication whatever.</p>
            <p>Nor am I aſham'd on this, to entitle this Treatiſe, to the ſtile of an Entire Vindication of the Doctor; for what thô the Doctor be not infallible, nor his Reaſonings the unaltera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Standard of Wiſdom? that is not a Character he ever preſum'd at, nor that could ever be expected from him, the rational Vindication to be expected therefore, either of the Doctor, or any Man elſe, is, that he has kept in the track of Vertue, and preſerv'd his ſincerity entire; and if that can be maintain'd, I preſume, we may very well bear with a perfect <hi>Salvo</hi> to the Doctor's Reputation; nay, and Parts too, notwithſtanding he is not infallible.</p>
            <p>And methinks it grieves me here, that I am forc'd as it were to go between the skin and the fleſh, to ſeem to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the Method of Mr. <hi>Per.</hi> and to vindicate a Doctrine I can by no means approve of; methinks, I ſay, this ſeems of great difficulty to me; for I always had too great an eſteem for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties, to diſreſpect their true Patriots; and on the other hand, injur'd Innocence on the Doctor's ſide, has forc'd me to take his part againſt them.</p>
            <p>Therefore Reader, excuſe me that I do this Office for the Doctor, nor be ſurprized, why I ſhould do it, that am his Adverſary in ſome things. Who was that, that dar'd the fury of the Prieſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the late Reign, in all their Controverſies, was it no the Doctor? Who was it durſt then aſſault Popery,
<pb facs="tcp:43577:3"/>not only with the vigorouſeſt Reaſons, but with his open Name to his Books, was it not Dr. <hi>Sherlock?</hi> indeed, who was more eminent in all thoſe Controverſies than he?</p>
            <p>When the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Magdalen-Colledge,</hi> became Confeſſors to the late Tyde of Romiſh Tyranny, and when Dr. <hi>Sharp</hi> was ſilenc'd, did he recant his Proceedings, did he dread the imminent Dangers, or was he afraid of the threatned Oppreſſion, or did he not rather like a ſtout Champion for the Church, ſtand unconcern'd in the midſt of theſe things? And muſt the Doctor then, now, become the only Object of our Contempt, muſt a little point of Caſuiſm, make him too mean to live amongst us?</p>
            <p>Are we all Proteſtants, are we all reſolv'd against the Common Enemy, the <hi>Romaniſts?</hi> If we are, I ſay, how can this method he accountable with our deſigns? not, I ſay, that therefore we ſhould thro' reſpect of Perſons, let the Doctor lead us blindfold; but as we ſhould not, ſo we ſhould not for our own ſakes, let every little Controverſie ruine the Reputation of ſuch a Man.</p>
            <p>I cannot think the World fond to deſire the Doctor to be an ill Man, that they might make that out in matter of fact, and truth, that ſome of his Enemies have too much already done in pretences; I ſay, I cannot be ſo uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but if they do not, let them for their own Credit treat him better for the future.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, as for the general unreaſonableneſs of his Tenets in this matter, it is not the work of a Preface; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, thus much I ſhall ſay, that the Doctor has not unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly the Name of an eminent Reaſoner; and if in ſome things his Notions are not exactly accountable to us, we have no reaſon to admire; for had any of us laid our Breaſts ſo freely open in our Writings, as he has done, I may add, the best of us, 'tis not impoſſible, but that ſome of the World, had we as great a Post, would give us as hard a Cenſure as ever the Doctor had.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pamphlet">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43577:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF <hi>Dr. Sherlock, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHEN a Man is unfairly Proſecuted and Libell'd rather than Anſwer'd, and when the Croud of Mobile-Writers break in upon him, as if they would cruſh and murder his Reputation with their Numbers, even his very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, if they have any Generoſity, ought to ſtep in to ſupport him; indeed, 'tis the common Cauſe of all Mankind not to ſee any man unjuſtly ſuffer, and therefore though in ſome things I differ from the Doctor in Judgment, yet I cannot but reſcue him from thoſe Aſperſions that are ſo baſely caſt upon him.</p>
            <p>But as his Adverſaries are now grown to ſuch a number, and their Arguments for the moſt part a borrow'd Tautology and Plagiariſm from each other, that except ſome few they almoſt all write the ſame thing, ſo I ſhall neither give my ſelf nor the Reader
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43577:4"/>that trouble, as to trace out all their little crooked Paths, but examining the ſum of all their Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Doctor, at leaſt of all thoſe that are conſiderable, I ſhall briefly, and generally, as if they were all but one, ſhew how little he deſerves their ill treatment, and how eminent an Example he is of Innocence abus'd.</p>
            <p>Without therefore particularly regarding either the Vindications or Anſwers that the Doctor has had upon this Subject, for that were endleſs, and were too perplex'd a Method to do him Juſtice by; I ſay therefore, without hinting at either Perſons or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, I ſhall take the Liberty to make ſome few Reflections on the chief Points in Controverſie, in favour of the Doctor, and if any of his Adversaries think themſelves therein aggriev'd, I'le promiſe them they ſhall not want a reaſonable Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>But it may be objected, That under this Pretence perhaps I ſhall conceal or ſlur over thoſe things that may be moſt conſiderable, and only Vindicate the Doctor in thoſe that are obvious or trifling; I ſay as to that, the World will judge, and will ſee when they have read what I write; but if at the entrance it can encourage them to know whether I am not conſcious to my own defects in it or not, I aſſure them, I know nothing that is material that is objected againſt him, but is reconcileable to the Doctor as a Learned, Ingenious, and Sincere Man; and if his Adverſaries can ſee any thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I ſhall leave them to ſhew it.</p>
            <p>To proceed therefore, I ſay then firſt, is it ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous for Twenty men together to throng in their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43577:4"/>Anſwers to one Man? Indeed, is it not juſt as if they were afraid of having Replies, or at beſt, that thruſting thus into the Throng, they might eſcape the better for their being in the Multitude; and yet not I mean, that I believe that all thoſe Gentlemen that have wrote againſt him have had ſo mean a Deſign neither; but I ſay in general, is it a Credit for any man to be caught among the Mobile, and giving an Eminent Divine an ill Name, when at the ſame time he has all <hi>Billingsgate</hi> upon his back?</p>
            <p>Methinks, I ſay, theſe Gentlemen, for as for the others they ſcarce deſerve to be taken notice of; and therefore I ſay, methinks the choice and flower of the Doctor's Adverſaries, had they been brave, might have waited till the Doctor had been in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to Anſwer them, and not Aſſault him as they have done, where they could have no ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal proſpect for a return; I would only ask them one Queſtion, when they ſo much as favour ſo dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a proceeding in others, in Writing after them, do they not as good as half take their Guilt upon them? Is this their doing Juſtice to their Cauſe? Indeed, is this their doing as they would be done unto?</p>
            <p>In ſhort, Gentlemen, ſuppoſing the Doctor in ſome meaſure to blame, and taking it for granted he deſerv'd your Anſwers, yet when ſome for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, ſome through Miſtake, and ſome for Gain, had thus meanly and diſingenuouſly attempted to deface his Reputation in what he deſerved not, would you after this pretend to any thing like Honour, and yet back them in their proceedings? Surely Sirs, for the future, if Generoſity cannot move you,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43577:5"/>yet Humanity, nay, your own Intereſt and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ought to make you more wary; methinks in ſuch caſe, rather than fail, you ſhould Vindicate him your ſelves, at worſt you ſhould leave ſuch little Raylors alone to expoſe themſelves upon him.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, Sirs, if you have a mind for the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Common Wittiſts, Buffoons, and Merce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, write on; but if you have not, ingenuouſly retract your Methods and Proceedings, and ceaſe to Triumph at trampled-on Innocence; and to vent your Spleens, where I am perſwaded, had you bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſider'd your ſelves, and were you not rather Bruits than Men, you would turn your Aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
            <p>Beſides, Gentlemen, give me leave to tell you, I mean ſome of the beſt of you, I cannot accuſe you all, for ſome of you have wrote as becomes Gentlemen, had you not throng'd your ſelves into the Croud; but ſome of you, I am afraid too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, have wrote as if you had neither Charity nor Juſtice in your Cenſures; you have demeaned your ſelves like Tyrants in your peremptory Deciſions, and treated the Doctor no better than if he were the worſt of Men.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not hint at any particular Anſwers in this matter, becauſe I had rather ſmother than increaſe the flame; and though the Doctor's Adverſaries have had but little Charity in ſparing him, yet his Friends think to take another courſe, and as they apprehend would become him, are willing rather if poſſible to overcome evil with good, and to ſhew them whatever raſh Judgments they have been
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43577:5"/>guilty of, they do not delight in Recriminations, tho' poſſibly they might make them even with Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>However in general to point at ſome of your Guilts; and to ſhew you I do not write without good Grounds, pray but reflect a little: Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity bids us not think eaſily any evil of our Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but put the beſt ſence and conſtruction upon his words and actions: but you will out-face us, he means ill, tho' he declares his ſincerity; whilſt you know after that, that none but God can cenſure him, that alone knows his Heart. Thus one tells him, his Wife ſways him; another inſinuates, that 'tis Preferments without his Wife; and a third, that his Pride has born him to this ſingula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <p>But, Sirs, whilſt you did thus, I am afraid you forgot what might be ſaid of your ſelves, I mean juſtly of you that cenſure ſo; the Doctor may be in the right, as I am perſwaded he is, but you as falſe Judges muſt be in the wrong; nay more, were the Doctor corrupt in his Proteſtations, which far be it from us to think, yet if there were but a poſſibility that he might be ſincere, I am ſure nothing can excuſe you from the guilt of a mean, wilful, and uncharitable Slander.</p>
            <p>And I write this the rather, on the ſuppoſition of the truth of the worſt Character, that your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectural thoughts can give the Doctor, becauſe the leaſt lurking-hole may not be left for your Apology; in plain terms, to ſhew the World, that nothing but Braſs, Impudence, and meer Jack-pudding Grin, can excuſe ſome of the Doctor's Enemies, and a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43577:6"/>diſhonourable and uncharitable Careleſneſs, moſt of the beſt of them in their proeeedings.</p>
            <p>Had they in general ſhew'd the Inconſiſtency of the Doctor's Reaſoning, and the Danger of it to the State; and had they upon this exhorted him modeſtly to re-conſider, and thereon to renounce his new and ill-grounded Opinion, they had acted ſomething like Chriſtians: but point blank, the firſt word, to accuſe even a Father in the Church of Corruption and Deſign, before any proof to juſtifie it, indeed before the offer of a Conviction by ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Arguments; I ſay, to proceed thus perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and raſhly, and to anticipate all hopes of his vindicating himſelf in a Reply, thro' their unjuſt Sentence paſt upon him, is to Execute him firſt, and Try him after; and a piece of Juſtice, that of itsſelf alone, with any Man either of Honour or Honeſty, were enough to vindicate the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</p>
            <p>But for once, I ſhall paſs by theſe two little faults in the Doctor's Adverſaries; to wit, want of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity and Charity; for 'tis poſſible the Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties the Doctor has committed in his Vindication, has fir'd them to over-ſee themſelves to this degree in their Anſwers: and therefore, becauſe as the Doctor's Friend, who I am perſwaded would not ſerve them ſo himſelf, I ſhall ſhew them, I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to allow them all the fair Play imaginable, and therefore we will ſee what it is they have to ſay to his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>In the Doctor's Cauſe, then I ſay there are two things principally which they are offended at; the Firſt, That it is very diſagreeable to the State. And
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43577:6"/>the Second, That it is unreaſonable. Now as to both theſe, I ſhall give them brief and ſolid An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers; and tho', as I have ſaid, I am not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Doctor's Mind; yet 'tis becauſe I think he has not a ſufficient ground in Revelation, and not in Reaſon, as his Adverſaries charge him; and therefore I do not doubt, I ſay, from their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to ſhew them, that they have but little reaſon to be ſo offended with him.</p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe two Objections, to wit, The diſagreeableneſs of the Doctor's Principles to the State, I ſhall return two Anſwers; the firſt, That his Adverſaries have abus'd him, and put a worſe ſence upon his words, when they were very well capable of a better. And Secondly, That even in the very ſence they have taken them, they ſtate an Hypotheſis as agreeable to the State as any of them, I may ſay the very beſt of them have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, I ſay, when the Doctor laid it down as a Principle, That whoever was ſetled in a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, I mean peaceably, and by conſent, had God's Authority, tho' he at firſt attain'd it by force; I ſay, when the Doctor laid down theſe Propoſitions, what did he do, but as it were declare, that a King by Conqueſt and Conſent after it was a good King, and whether he were an Uſurper before or not, I challenge all his Adverſaries to diſprove his Title.</p>
            <p>Now I ſay, when the Doctor's Principles can ſo juſtly reſolve themſelves into a Conqueſt, and tho' not of the People, yet of the King, by, and through the Conſent of the People; I ſay, when the Doctor
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43577:7"/>by this prudently choſe a middle way, to avoid the <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Caribdis</hi> of Paſſive-Obedience and Reſiſtance, methinks his Adverſaries might have been ſo inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious, as to have underſtood him ſo, and not to have preſt him to a nice deciſion, which be it pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued home of either ſide, muſt needs offend the State.</p>
            <p>Now whether what the Doctor in this Caſe has laid down, will amount to a Right of Conqueſt or not, ſhall be made to appear more plainly by and by; but if it does, as I do not queſtion but I ſhall be able to make out, 'tis plain, how diſingenuouſly his Adverſaries have dealt with him. Let him call it a Divine Right, and let them expect him to call it a Legal Right; yet as what he has wrote, has evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently amounted to a Right by Conqueſt, as good a Right as Mortal need deſire to poſſeſs in a juſt Cauſe; I ſay, as it amounts to that, and as that is evidently the drift of the Doctor's Reaſonings, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks they needed not to have diſtorted him from it.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, even in their own way, in their tacking this Principle to Paſſive-Obedience, and ſo endeavouring to expoſe it, with all the abſurd Conſequences they can draw from both together; I ſay, even in that dreſs, it appears more likely to be agreeable to the State, than any thing his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries have ſet up; in plain terms, the State has as much reaſon to be diſobliged at their Title, with its Conſequences, from Reſiſtance, and from the Doctor's Title, and Conſequences from Paſſive-Obedience.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43577:7"/>
            <p>The Doctor ſets up Force and the Conſent of the People, to transfer God's Authority; and his Adverſaries ſay, The Choice of the People gives a Legal Right. Thus the Doctor ſeems to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oblige the Prince, by denying him verbally a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Right: but his Adverſaries do as bad, when they ſhew him by Example, that he is to bear Rule only <hi>Durante Beneplacito,</hi> of the giddy Mobb. But what? you ſay his Adverſaries Complement him with a Legal Right; 'tis true, they do: but as their fickle Caſe ſtands, I don't know whether Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Divine Right, and Paſſive-Obedience, may not be more acceptable to them.</p>
            <p>And what then, is the Caſe come to this? The King then has ſurely great reaſon to be beholding to theſe his <hi>Durante Beneplacito</hi> Men, and to be aggriev'd at the Doctor's Methods; they honour him with a Legal Right indeed: but they tack it ſo to Abdications and Forfeitures, that a Man had better be Tenant at Will to a good Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, than Abſolute Monarch on ſuch Terms, and to depend ſo much upon every giddy reliſh of a factious Populace.</p>
            <p>I ſay then, iſ this be the Caſe, as it manifeſtly is, with thoſe that give the King a Legal Right, from the Depoſing the late King <hi>James,</hi> and the chooſing Their Preſent Majeſties; I ſay, if this be the Caſe, I am ſure the Doctor's Principles are not half ſo likely to be offenſive to the Government, as his Adverſaries, and therefore on their own ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, they have brought in this as a Motive for their Writing, againſt all the ſence and reaſon in the World.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:43577:8"/>
            <p>In ſhort, can his Adverſaries have the Face to ſay, that when a Man has acknowledg'd a King inveſted with God's Authority, without the words of Legal Right, that he can half ſo much diſoblige the Government, as he that lays down Principles (or at leaſt implies them) of Abdication and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, Principles that like the <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> at beſt ought to be kept ſecret, and not preach'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, if allow'd, and that like Swords in Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens and Mad-mens hands, ought not too free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be truſted in the hands of a giddy Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
            <p>Indeed, had his Adverſaries but modeſtly urg'd, that he had better have concealed his Reaſons to himſelf, than ſo have urg'd them to offend the State, I had agreed with them, had it been only on the probability, that what he has wrote might have af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded offence; and yet not, I ſay, but that me-thinks too, if he has given offence, by not granting a Legal Right, he has made it up again by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right; and if what he has wrote may be taken in an evil ſence, it may alſo receive a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>So that in truth, the ſuggeſtions of the Doctor's Anſwerers are to be blam'd, and not the Doctor; and indeed, whatever they pretend, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is as much obliged to them, as a Man on Horſeback to a Stander-by, that tickles his Horſe, when he knows he is us'd upon it to throw his Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and whether like cunning States-men, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Water-men, they oppoſe the Doctor ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly for the Government; but really as they are againſt it; whether they Look one way, and Row
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43577:8"/>another, or not, I dare not be ſo uncharitable as to cenſure; but as I dare not, yet this is manifeſt, and may be averr'd, this ſeems the natural effect and tendency of their proceedings.</p>
            <p>And indeed, this brings it to my mind, that the Doctor has <hi>Jacobite</hi> Enemies as well as others, and may be could one ſee the bottom, one would find, that 'tis from them that the greateſt part of this Fire is kindled; and in truth, as manifeſt as it is, methinks his other Adverſaries ſhould be aſham'd to perſecute him as they do. St. <hi>Paul</hi> could rejoyce, that Chriſt was preach'd, tho' even in Contention, and really, did the moſt Loyal of the Doctor's Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, rather ſeek the good of the Government, than the meer reſentments of their Spleens and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, they would be glad, that the Doctor had brought in this New Principle of Allegiance, were it only to bring over, if poſſible, thoſe Members that diſſented from the Government for Paſſive-Obedience, and not quarrel with him for the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty of it.</p>
            <p>And really when I conſider this, methinks I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but admire to ſee, how much Men are blinded by the fondneſs of Opinion, that they can rather bear to ſacrifice their Intereſt, than to allow the leaſt latitude in their Caſuiſtical Deciſions, that they will rather fright every body that is coming into the Government, than embrace them, if not exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their Sentiments; in ſhort, an arrogant Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, and as Enthuſiaſtick, and as much againſt all the natural Principles of Self-defence, as ever can be pretended of Paſſive-Obedience, at the worſt of it.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43577:9"/>
            <p>But to turn my Argument to thoſe <hi>Jacobites,</hi> that under the pretext and colour of Paſſive-Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, would fain deſtroy our preſent Settlement and Allegiance; I ſay, as to them, methinks the Doctor's Argument is as full and convincing, as either they can expect, or the nature of the thing can bear; and 'tis well for thoſe, that the Doctor has ſo many Enemies to keep them in countenance, that they might be the better able to withſtand his Reaſonings.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, if the Doctor's Adverſaries Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the Right of Reſiſtance cannot move them; yet the Doctor's from the Right of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt muſt do it; or elſe there is no Prince may be in the World, at leaſt very few, have any Rights, at beſt, originally to their Thrones. In truth, the Doctor's Right by Conqueſt is as well the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive, as the moſt juſtifiable Title. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the Doctor's King, ſetled quietly, and entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the Conſent of the People in poſſeſſion, is the Reſiſtances's Man King by a new Election; and were the Quarrels about Words taken away, they would amount to juſt the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>No, but you ſay, 'tis the Election gives the Title, and not the Conſent to poſſeſſion; I ſay, 'tis falſe: the Conſent to Poſſeſſion argues an Election, tho' not a Formal one; and 'tis ſuch an Election, that no Chriſtian, I am ſure, can evade with a ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; indeed, without Men will be treacherous, and that barbarouſly too, they owe Allegiance where they receive Protection, and he muſt neither pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to Generoſity, Honour, or Conſcience, that will not pay it.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:43577:9"/>
            <p>A Generous Enemy will ſcorn to ſtoop to ſo mean a Diſſimulation, a Man of Honour would take the Field againſt ſuch an Uſurper, and a Man of the leaſt Conſcience, would ſooner die than he would play the Viper in the Fable, ſting him to Death that gave him warmth and life, or at the beſt pretence, do Evil that Good might come, and ungratefully receive the Courteſies of a Friend, the more baſely to do the viler, I ſhould ſay Offices unworthy of an Enemy.</p>
            <p>Indeed Popery, as it has corrupted our Religion, ſo it has our Morals alſo, and has made even Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to do thoſe things, that the honeſter Heathens would bluſh at; but as they have, I hope we will not corrupt with them, and think to conquer them by out-villaning of them; but rather bravely, at leaſt our ſelves, be good and honeſt, and deter them from their black and deviliſh Practices, by a Vengeance and Reſentment ſuitable to their Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if there be either Laws or Rights of War and Peace, a Government by Conſent is as juſt as by Election, and as ſecure a bottom to found it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and if Men are reſolv'd to cavil, they may juſtlier do it at a Right thro' Election, than Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: for inſtance, When a Government is diſſolv'd, (pardon the expreſſion) why am I bound to ſtand to any Man, or Councils Election for me, why ſhall ſome Vills, and yet not ſome whole Cities, ſend Members to Conventions? Indeed, were I not by the Laws of God, bound to ſtudy and follow the beſt Methods of Peace, where were otherwiſe my Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to theſe things?</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43577:10"/>
            <p>And therefore I ſay, the Doctor's Argument, that as God manifeſtly allows, indeed requires Changes in State, ſo he confirms the New Model, by its entire Settlement, is irrefragable, againſt all the Attacks either of Paſſive-Obedience, or Reſiſtance-Men in the World, and the Objection about Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers againſt it, is as idle as weak; in plain terms, we exclaim in Complement to New and Rightful Princes, at the removal of Uſurpers; but in truth, whoever by Force, or otherwiſe, has once ſecur'd to himſelf peaceably, the poſſeſſion and enjoyment of a Throne, is at leaſt to his Subjects as good a King, as either the Right of Conqueſt or Election can make him.</p>
            <p>Has the Uſurper no Right, why do you tranſmit it then to him by a puſillanimous ſubmiſſion; and why do you not at the firſt approach of the wrong, fly to Arms and Councels to reſiſt the Injuſtice, and to ſupport the injur'd Prince? But if baſely you once ſacrifice your Loyalty, and his Right, by at leaſt an implicite Contract of Allegiance; think you like a Coward and an Arch-Traytor, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to re-aſſume that Right you have reſign'd, and meanly to take advantages from your own Villany.</p>
            <p>Nay more, to puſh this Argument home further, ſuch a Title thro' Poſſeſſion exceeds all the Elections in the World, a quiet Poſſeſſion ſhews a compleat Election, whilſt a formal one, by a Convention, or otherwiſe, may be corrupt and packt, and more unjuſt and illegal than the Tyrant and Uſurper him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; in plain terms, were any Convention or Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſo packt, and can you think any honeſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43577:10"/>thereupon bound to leave his Lawful Soveraign againſt his Conſent and Conſcience? which 'tis evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, when either by inadvertency or Treachery he has ſuffer'd an Uſurper, even for but a Month to enjoy quiet poſſeſſion he is bound to do.</p>
            <p>Having therefore I hope ſufficiently clear'd the Doctor hitherto, I ſhall try to deſcend a little fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to free him from thoſe Calumnies that are caſt againſt him from the Topicks of Paſſive-Obedience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not but that his Adverſaries, as I have obſerv'd have dealt very unfairly with him in this thing; for when his Argument, as I have ſhewn, might juſtly have been maintain'd without the leaſt thought of Paſſive-Obedience, or affronting the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; I ſay, what needed his Adverſaries to bring in thoſe things upon it; indeed does it not ſeem meerly as it were to calumniate him, as if they would inſinuate all that the Doctor has wrote is wrong, becauſe we have already prejudicated him in that one Error of Paſſive-Obedience?</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, as I am by all Circumſtances hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto convinc'd of the Doctor's Integrity, and as this prejudice of Paſſive-Obedience is reflected upon him, whether beſides the purpoſe or not, at preſent I ſhall not regard; but as I am reſolv'd to vindicate him thoroughly, and as the proſpect of his Cauſe doth not afford me any thing to diſcourage me, ſo I do not doubt but to ſhew his Adverſaries, that for all what they have wrote againſt Paſſive-Obedience, it is not ſo contemptible a Doctrine, that a Man ſhould be hooted out of the World for it, or that the Doctor ſhould loſe his Reputation thro' profeſſing it.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43577:11"/>
            <p>And I venture to write this, as I have ſaid, tho' I do not believe the Doctrine myſelf, for as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments the Doctors Adverſaries inſiſt upon againſt it are Irrationalneſs and Enthuſiaſm, and as mine is from quite another Topick, the want of clear Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation for it, I ſay as we reaſon quite from different grounds, and as I apprehend his Adverſaries grounds very inſufficient, I think I may juſtly vindicate the Doctrine as to them, tho' I neither believe it, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire to ſet it up myſelf; and this I conceive will be a ſufficient Vindication of the Doctor in the Caſe, that tho' he may be in an Errour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 'tis not ſo groſs as they would ſuggeſt, nor indeed in any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular like unto any that they have alledg'd againſt him.</p>
            <p>Nor ſhall I in this Caſe make any Apology for the Doctor, that we might juſtly bear with him in this prejudice, when a Univerſity, indeed a whole Kingdom near once gave him its encouragement in it; and yet this methinks, I might juſtly ſay to his Adverſaries, ſurely, had their Zeal been ſo great meerly againſt the Doctrine of Paſſive-Obedience, they might have vented it, without flinging all the Dirt of it upon one Man; indeed, to prevent them from the Uncharitableneſs of particular Reflections, they would have done more honourably to have fell upon the Univerſity itsſelf, that many Years ſince, burnt all the Propoſitions in contradiction to it.</p>
            <p>And as I ſhall not inſiſt upon this prejudice, ſo I ſhall not upon another, may I ſay, full as conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to wit, with what deliberation and thought, Men of true Piety alter their Opinions; I ſay, I ſhall not inſiſt on theſe things, tho' yet I take the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43577:11"/>liberty to hint at them, be it only to ſhew the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's Adverſaries, that even theſe very prejudices, how trifling ſoever they may appear, yet they might juſtly have mov'd them to a greater Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and Charity in their Cenſures; but as I have ſaid, I ſhall not inſiſt on theſe things, but ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing for the Cauſe itsſelf (for all the Objections that have been made againſt it) I ſhall ſhew, that 'tis neither ſo ſcandalous, nor ſo ſenceleſs as has been imagin'd.</p>
            <p>Now the better to do this, I ſhall ſtate the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt this Doctrine of Paſſive-Obedience, under two heads, <hi>viz.</hi> the firſt, The general Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of it. And the ſecond, Its Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm. As for the Scripture-proof of it, as I have ſaid, I ſhall not ſo much concern myſelf about it, becauſe it has not been any ways made uſe of as the Foundational Argument, and therefore, I ſay, I ſhall leave that to what the Doctor hath already wrote upon it.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore, as to the general Unreaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it: I would fain ask the Doctor's Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, what it is they think more reaſonable. What, Reſiſtance? I ſay, it muſt be that, if any thing, for there is no mean; and this is manifeſt, 'tis the Duty of the Clergy to acquaint their Flock of one or other, when they conſult them Caſuiſtically; I ſay, therefore let us ſuppoſe theſe two ſet together in compariſon, and let us ſee which is the moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable of them.</p>
            <p>Paſſive-Obedience leaves all to the Fury of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; Reſiſtance to the Rage of the Rabble: but you ſay, the Rabble may be reſtrain'd of ſuch their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43577:12"/>Right of Reſiſtance, by (at leaſt unjuſt) Laws (for ſo you muſt call them in ſuch caſe); and ſo I ſay, the Prince will be reſtrain'd from his Tyranny, by means of Paſſive-Obedience, thro' the fear of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Reſiſtance in his Subjects.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, you object the miſchiefs that have enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon Paſſive-Obedience; and I tell you, as great have follow'd the giddineſs of Reſiſtance; or if you cannot believe what I write in this matter, on my bare aſſeveration, and want an example, pray examine <hi>Matchiavel</hi>'s Hiſtory of <hi>Florence,</hi> and there you will find it ſet out effectually; indeed, we do not ſee ſo many Examples of the Tyranny and Miſchiefs of Reſiſtance in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as of the Arbitrarineſs of <hi>Nero's;</hi> but the reaſon is, becauſe that few States have been fram'd ſo, as to tolerate ſuch free Reſiſtances, and which indeed is a plain and experimental Argument, that one Tyrant is more tolerable and eaſie than many.</p>
            <p>So that in plain terms, both ways are extreams, and equally unreaſonable, and if either be ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, 'tis Paſſive-Obedience, which ſeems an Error on the right hand, and in favour of Government; and yet for all that, in truth, the Controverſie is as dangerouſly touch'd on the one ſide, as the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Error of both ſides is, that Men would vainly endeavour to bring the Actions of Man to a ſteady Rule; when alas, he is too giddy a Creature, to bear it.</p>
            <p>In plain terms, a Free State ſhould neither ſuffer any Man to preach up Paſſive-Obedience, nor Reſiſtance; neither Paſſive-Obedience, I ſay, for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43577:12"/>fear of ſlaving it, nor Reſiſtance for fear of em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broiling it; and indeed, if Men have honeſt and peaceable Intentions, they may very well be content to preach up Obedience to Governours, without touching at the nice Caſuiſme of it, of either ſide.</p>
            <p>Nor is it enough in ſuch Caſe to ſay, that you can define the exact Rule of Reſiſtance, where, and in what Caſe it ought to be us'd; for the ſame may be alledg'd for the Doctrine of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive-Obedience; for even the Teachers of that Doctrine have declared and limited the Authority of Princes alſo, that they might not abuſe their Power; I ſay, theſe defining and caſuiſtical Deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Reſiſtance and Command, will do no more good on the one ſide, than the other; for put the Sword either into the hands of the Prince or Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, there's equal danger that either of them may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe it.</p>
            <p>I think therefore the Doctor's Adverſaries have had but little reaſon to charge him with the Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of Paſſive-Obedience, when they ſet up Reſiſtance themſelves; indeed, had they bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rejected Paſſive-Obedience as unſcriptural, and not endeavoured by Reaſoning to undermine it with a Doctrine rais'd from Topicks of a far worſe conſequence. I mean, had they inſinuated to him, that he had done better, had he relied meerly on the Right of Conqueſt, without hinting at Paſſive-Obedience; then, I ſay, they would have had the Juſtice of the Cauſe of their ſide, and their Demands had been modeſt and reaſonable, and poſſibly what the Doctor would never have denied
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43577:13"/>them, for the very drift of his Reaſoning tends the ſame way; but the Unreaſonableneſs tax'd on his Principles from their Grounds and Reaſonings, has not the leaſt manner of colour for it.</p>
            <p>The Second Objection that I am to anſwer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Paſſive-Obedience, is the Enthuſiaſm of it; a Charge as I find flung upon it, becauſe out of its abundant Confidence in God, it flings a Man up into the very Jaws of Danger, without ſo much as the very thought of Self-defence; I ſay, this ſeems a very formidable Objection againſt Paſſive-Obedience; but when we come to handle it, it moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders away to nothing.</p>
            <p>Previouſly therefore to this matter, and to clear the Controverſie about it, I ſhall define what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Enthuſiaſm, and what not. I ſay, then to offer at a private Revelation, or any private Rule of Faith from unwarranted Conceit, is Enthuſiaſm; but only to truſt the known Revelation, was never called Enthuſiaſm properly, and by any Man of Sence that ever I knew yet.</p>
            <p>I ſay therefore, the Doctor in following ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Scriptures, tho' in a miſtake, is no more guilty of Enthuſiaſm, than his Adverſaries are of Innocence in ſlandering him with it. This may be indeed, the Doctor may be in an Error in interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Scriptures, as I believe he is: and if he is, they would have done well to undeceive him; but then, if they would, they ſhould have ſtudied to have done it with that ſincerity and candour, that their Methods might not prejudice him faſter, then their Arguments convince him; or elſe they would have but little right left to the claim of Charity, and good Intention in the caſe.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43577:13"/>
            <p>But methinks I hear it objected, That this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is not ſufficient, that the truſting in God, and omitting Self-defence ſtill remains, and 'tis that is the Enthuſiaſm; I ſay it is not, but it is Faith, and poſſibly not ſo unaccountable a one as ſome Men imagine neither; indeed is there not an Example in the <hi>Jews</hi> where a whole Nation thus truſted in God for their Deliverance, nay, and that more then once too, and was deliver'd accordingly.</p>
            <p>Nor is it an argument in ſuch caſe, that becauſe we have not ſeen any example of ſuch Deliverance of late, that therefore we may not expect it, if the World be generally ſo vile as not to deſerve ſuch a Protection from God, ſhall we therefore be wicked in deſpair of it, in ſhort, becauſe the cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Mens faith has now reduc'd it to be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly without efficacy, ſhall we therefore fling Faith itſelf aſide.</p>
            <p>But to illuſtrate this by Example: The Martyrs in Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s days they truſted in God, and quitted their Self defence, nay, and that to a great number together; yes, and more after that Queen <hi>Mary</hi> both corruptly, and contrary to the moſt ſolemn Engagments, had violated the Laws, and perſecuted them, I ſay, after all this, yet they through their truſt in God, quitted their Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and Right of Reſiſtance, and yet no one that ever I knew, called them Enthuſiaſts.</p>
            <p>Indeed by the Principles of Reſiſtance they might have concluded the whole State, King, Queen, Lords, and Commons void, if not for their unjuſt Law of deſtroying for Religion, meer Religion I mean, yet at leaſt as the firſt had broken their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43577:14"/>Truſts, and the latter were rather packed then le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally call'd to their Aſſembly, I ſay, by the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Reſiſtance they might juſtly have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded thus; but as they did not, and did not fly to reſolve themſelves to their firſt Elements the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lords the People, I ſay, though they did not, yet I hope we may juſtly give them the Titles of Martyrs through Faith, without branding them with Enthuſiaſm.</p>
            <p>In plain terms, at this rate at laſt we ſhall drive Martyrdom out of the World, and he will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted equally Fool and Coward that does not dye with his Sword in his hand: Is Martyrdom in a great many private Men a Duty, I may ſay to half the People, as has lately near happen'd in <hi>France;</hi> I ſay, why is it not in Kingdoms alſo, doth Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſm <hi>recipere magis &amp; minus,</hi> or is it to hold in all caſes alike; indeed why muſt we be Enthuſiaſts in part through a Revelation, and not throughout; ſo that 'tis plain theſe Men muſt either quite reject Martyrdom with Paſſive Obedience, or elſe ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknowledge, that laying aſide all the Abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of reaſoning in it, they will with me whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rely on the Authority of the Scriptures for it.</p>
            <p>So that the reaſoning of the matter will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved thus: All People that have truſted in God through Paſſive Obedience, have not been deliver'd with the <hi>Iſraelites;</hi> no more have not all Martyrs like <hi>Shadrack, Meſhack</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> been deliver'd from the power of Flames and Tortures; I ſay, therefore as we are not to expect always our Faith to ſucceed in the latter caſe of Martydom, ſhall we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43577:14"/>be ſo unreaſonable as to murmur and repine that Sufferings are likely to befal us in the other, and for that reaſon only to conclude it cannot be a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon us?</p>
            <p>In ſhort, I know no other way that the Doctor's Enthuſiaſtical Adverſaries have to evade the force of this reaſoning, unleſs by pretending that 'tis one thing to reſiſt the King that has only the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Power, and another to reſiſt the Fountain or Legiſlative Power; and as I have ſhew'd that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not help them, for under the pretence even of the Parliament's being pack'd, or Penſioners, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance Men will allow themſelves to oppoſe the Legiſlative Power alſo; ſo that we may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Principle of Reſiſtance can ſcarce ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally admit a Man in ſuch circumſtances as to be a Martyr, and if it does not by that treſpaſs as much on the ſide of Infidelity and Diffidence in God, as Paſſive Obedience does on Enthuſiaſm, I am very much miſtaken.</p>
            <p>Nor indeed is this the only paralel Caſe to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this ſort of Enthuſiaſm, wherein a Man ſo truſts in God as to give up himſelf, for if all ſuch courſes muſt imply a ridiculous Enthuſiaſm, Faith it ſelf muſt be ridiculous alſo: Thus <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt be an Enthuſiaſt for leaving his Father's Country: And the Chriſtian that beſtows a Charity is an Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt for parting with that preſent ſupply, that by poſſibility he may ſtand in need of.</p>
            <p>So that I hope I may now very well conclude, I have acquitted the Doctor from all pretence of Enthuſiaſm, when the very ſame Argument that his Adverſaries have brought to accuſe him with, as I
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43577:15"/>have manifeſtly ſhewn, will not only, if not ſoftned, ruine Paſſive Obedience, but even Chriſtianity, and all manner of Faith and Religion whatever alſo.</p>
            <p>And I think I may now draw to a Concluſion, and I hope to the general ſatisfaction alſo, for if I am not as much miſtaken as ever I was in my life, I have given the Doctor an effectual Vindication, I mean ſuch an one as is not only able to return the Dirt caſt upon him back upon his Adverſaries, but with all good Men to reſtore him to his former Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Eſteem.</p>
            <p>I think I have ſufficiently ſhewn to the World, that his Adverſaries are not generous, that they can aſſault him thus in Crouds; that they are not cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, that they can attribute Scandals to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the Rules of Sincerity and Honour; I have ſhewn moreover, that what he hath wrote may receive effectually a good ſence, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Scandal to the Government too, without Men are reſolv'd to force his Words to the worſt; and as I have ſhewn this, ſo I might have ſtaid here, and ſaid this is enough, had I thought fit only juſt to Vindicate his Cauſe.</p>
            <p>But for the ſatisfaction of his Enemies I have gone on further, I have ſhewn them his Doctrine of Paſſive Obedience is not ſo abſurd neither as they would inſinuate; in ſhort, I have ſhewn them it is as good as Reſiſtance, and let them make the worſt or it; and to this I have added, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſion of Enthuſiaſm on the Doctor, is manifeſtly an Injuſtice and a Reproach.</p>
            <p>To this I might add his Praying for King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> when he wiſhed King <hi>James</hi> the Succeſs, his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43577:15"/>Proteſting againſt his promoting Non-ſwearing, when at the ſame time when ask'd he gave his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and his Inconſtancy in changing his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and many other ſuch trifling Objections, that a good Man would be aſhamed to bring them; however his Adverſaries have alleadg'd them, and as thoſe three I have nam'd ſeem the moſt conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able of them, I have reſolv'd to give them the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction that their Objections are not Unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and then I hope they will be content to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs me.</p>
            <p>I ſay then the Doctor prayed for King <hi>William,</hi> he did ſo, and 'tis the Command of Chriſt to Pray for our Enemies, as I preſume the Doctor's Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then to K. <hi>James</hi> could not make him otherwiſe; I ſay then if he did this, and has Chriſt's Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to juſtifie him, what hurt is there in it? in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if the Doctor had us'd particular and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Expreſſions in his Prayer, he had been to blame, but as long as he deliver'd himſelf in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Terms, who ſhall accuſe him for it.</p>
            <p>When Chriſt bid us pray for our Enemies, did he command us to imply in ſuch our Prayers, that God would proſper them ſo as to confound and deſtroy us, or not rather that God would direct their hearts to ſave them, and move them to right us where they injur'd us? Surely I ſay the latter; and if that were ſo neceſſarily implied in the general Command of Chriſt to pray for our Enemies, ſhall we deny the Doctor that priviledge in the particular application of it.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay he nam'd him King when he did ſo; and what then, was it not then rationally a doubt in his thoughts, whether he were a King
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43577:16"/>or no? and if it was, might not he juſtly uſe the common Stile and Name he then went by, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Hypocriſie or Cowardize, when at the ſame time by his refuſing the Oaths he put the World out of all doubt of his Diſſimulation, I ſay, might he not honourably, as well as concientiouſly in ſuch a caſe Complement the King on his Doubt, at leaſt with the name of King.</p>
            <p>Indeed if he had had no Doubt upon him, but was convinc'd that he ought immediately to have help'd his diſtreſſed Prince, I ſay, then either he or any Man elſe under ſuch a Conviction, though they ought from the Command of Chriſt to pray for the new Prince, yet withal they ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to Complement him ſo far as to call him King, but, I ſay, when the Doctor was without any man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſuch Conviction, and was at leaſt ſatisfied that he was quit of his Aſſiſtance if not of his Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to his former Prince: Surely, I ſay, in ſuch caſe for his very Doubt's ſake the Doctor might Complement his new Prince with the name of King, eſpecially when ſetled by the Choice of the Nation in the Throne; and methinks no Caſuiſt in the World ſhould deny him that liberty.</p>
            <p>And in truth the Doctor's Enemies who pretend thus to refuſe to pray for the King, ought withal to remember, that they ought to act accordingly; they ought, as I have ſaid before, to declare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Hoſtile manner, and flie from his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for if they once baſely or lazily ſubmit to him, as I have before obſerved, they transfer their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and as long as the new King is in Poſſeſſion, they cannot retract without Treachery; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43577:16"/>they ought to pray for him as King alſo, if the Title they ſuffer him to uſurp be ſuch.</p>
            <p>And I might add to this alſo, that thoſe Men that are guilty of ſuch a mean and clandeſtine Treachery againſt the State, have the more reaſon in gratitude to her Mercy, to acknowledge her for the future; for however they harbour themſelves under the ſcruple of Paſſive-Obedience, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they ought to remember withal, that 'tis a ſingular Charity, may I ſay a greater, than ever they ſhew'd to the Doctor, that the State ſhews to them, in not treating them as Enemies; when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, without under a Prince of ſuch an unpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell'd Clemency, I don't know what they would well expect otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Charge againſt the Doctor, is, That he has chang'd his Opinion: right, and ſuppoſe he has, What have not others done it before him? or muſt it be an offence in the Doctor, only to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from a miſtake; but you ſay, he did it with deliberation: and it may be ſo; but what then, that ſhews him the more likely to be a Maſter of the greater Integrity in it, and not that he is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt; in plain terms, theſe Exceptions are rather Cavils than Reaſonings.</p>
            <p>When a Man ties himſelf to Principles by the Catalogue, I muſt confeſs he may be more conſtant than the Doctor; but when a Man allows himſelf free liberty of thinking, and ſicerity, he's a confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ignorant Pretender, that dares ſay, he ſhall not change his Opinion.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43577:17"/>
            <p>Nor is it difficult in ſuch Caſe to ſay, why ſome are longer in their change than others; for Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that give their Reaſon free reigns, purſue her at firſt ſight: corrupt Men act without Examining; but Divines that walk by a double ſight, Reaſon and Revelation; nay, ſometimes caſt in Tradition to them, may be fairly allow'd a longer time to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberate; and yet who ſhall ſay to a ſincere Man, juſt ſo long.</p>
            <p>The miſchief on't is, honeſt Men change their Minds out of Conviction, and Knaves out of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign; now the uncharitable World in this caſe, tho' it knows it cannot diſcern between theſe two, and therefore ought in all Caſes to put the beſt face on things; ſtreight without more ado, upon every little peck or paſſion cenſures Men, juſt as if they had got the ſole Prerogative of God in ſearching Mens Hearts.</p>
            <p>Nor is it enough in ſuch caſe to ſay, that ſuch a Man is Learned, and cannot but know better; for Men that ſay ſuch things, do but blindly diſcover their own preſumptuous Ignorance. Alas, there is no Caſuiſt can anſwer all Objections, even in the plaineſt Caſes; perfect Wiſdom is the Prerogative of God: and beſides, if they could, we ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how much ſuch Men as the Doctor are divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Publick, by his Sermons, by his writing neceſſary particular Tracts and Controverſies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing I propos'd to ſpeak to, is, that they find fault with the Doctor, for giving his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, when he would pretend himſelf free from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſing his Doctrine of Non-Swearing formerly. Now as to this, I ſay, it is a meer Calumny; and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43577:17"/>indeed, its own diſingeniouſneſs ſpeaks it ſo. To give our Opinion, when ask'd, of a thing, where good or evil, is a Duty that no Man can diſpenſe with in himſelf; and therefore, when the Doctor declared he was not for ſpreading his Doctrine, who would lay that upon him, that he could not avoid.</p>
            <p>Had he wrote Books to convince others upon it, or had he but wrote Letters to that purpoſe; nay, had he but ſought to promote the Subject and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie in diſcourſe, where he was not directed by a Letter for ſatisfaction, or a Friend, in a Caſuiſtick Queſtion; I ſay, had the Doctor's Adverſaries prov'd this, they might have ſhew'd this expreſſion of his inconſiſtency, and prov'd him guilty from his own words, of what he would inſinuate himſelf to be innocent; but to do as they have done, is to ſhew only that they would be glad of the occaſion for ſuch a falſe Judgment.</p>
            <p>All things therefore conſidered, I hope his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries will repent what they have been guilty of, and endeavour to repair that Reputation they have ſo unjuſtly injur'd. I am ſenſible what I can write in his defence, is not likely in all particulars to be ſo ſtrong, as what he himſelf might alledge; but as indeed the Cauſe is too naſty for the Doctor himſelf to meddle with, and as the apparent Merits of it on his part want little help to illuſtrate them, ſo I thought it better that a Stranger, I might ſay an Enemy, like myſelf, to the Doctor, ſhould undertake it, than he.</p>
            <p>I might add, that I could wiſh that the Task had fallen into a better hand; but ſince it is where it is, as I can ſolemnly before God ſatisfie myſelf of my
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43577:18"/>proceedings in this matter, ſo I ſhall endeavour to make them good; and if the Doctor's Enemies are reſolv'd on no Peace with him, I am reſolv'd on his behalf, to ſee how powerful they will prove in the Polemicks.</p>
            <p>All therefore that I ſhall deſire of his Enemies, for now if they perſiſt they are mine alſo is, but that they anſwer me with candour and ingenuity, with brevity and perſpicuity, and with ſolid ſence and integrity; and if ſo, they endeavour to refute what I have ſaid for the Doctor, I'll promiſe them, they ſhall not want as fair a Reply as they can wiſh for.</p>
            <p>But if notwithſtanding all has been ſaid, they will ſtill continue to Libel a Member formerly of the greateſt Reputation in the Church, and to whoſe Controverſies all Proteſtancy is oblig'd; I ſay, if ſuch Elders who as St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſes, muſt be treated with the greateſt reſpect, cannot have common Charity allow'd them; I ſay, if this be the temper of his Adverſaries, let it ſuffice the World, at leaſt the worthier part of it, that they revile him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, that they have had a tender of a fair ſatisfaction, and have refus'd it, whereupon all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind muſt acquit the Doctor, and reſtore him to their former eſteem, whilſt they wholly lay the blame and guilt upon his Enemies.</p>
            <p>But methinks I have a proſpect of better hope, of his Enemies, at beſt of the more conſiderable of them. It cannot be, that they ſhould perſiſt to do as they have done; nay, I am perſwaded they won't; for however they may charge Paſſive-Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43577:18"/>honourably with its Miſchiefs in their Zeal, yet they will not ſurely thus force an occaſion for it, they will no longer keep Men in fear from join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Government for being of that Principle, nor encourage the continuance of ſo unjuſt a ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; methinks, I ſay, for their own, nay, the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and Piety's ſake, they will ceaſe to perſiſt in this courſe longer. I end with the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</p>
            <q>Thou ſhalt not bear Falſe Witneſs against thy Neighbour.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PReface, p. 1. l. 23.</hi> Mr. <hi>Per. read</hi> Mr. <hi>Parkinſon; and in the laſt line</hi> was it no the Doctor, <hi>read</hi> was it not the Doctor. <hi>p. 8. l. 30.</hi> and from the Doctor's Title, <hi>read</hi> as from the Doctor's Title.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
